Guide to Garrett W. Price Papers, 1909-1976
University of Wyoming. American Heritage Center.
Garrett W. Price Papers
1909-1976
Price, Garrett W.
03202
5.47 cubic ft. (11 boxes)
University of Wyoming. American Heritage Center.
Garrett W. Price was a cartoonist best known for his work for "Life" and"The New Yorker". The collection contains artwork, diaries, correspondence, biographical material, and publications.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is arranged into 5 series.
Biography
Garrett W. Price was born in Bucyrus, Kansas in 1895. Garrett's father was a doctor and his practice took the family to several Western states, finally settling in Saratoga, Wyoming. Early on, Garrett showed an aptitude for drawing. His first cartoon was published by the "Saratoga Sun" in 1912. He entered the University of Wyoming in 1912 where he studied for two years before entering the Chicago Institute of Art. After graduating from there he was hired by the Art Department of the "Chicago Tribune" where he worked from 1916 to 1925. He illustrated stories for the Sunday Magazine, made two cartoons daily for the sports column, made one illustration a day for a serial, and laid out the roto section. Garrett also contributed some poetry to the "Tribune", but never under his own name. During World War I, he also found time to be the editorial cartoonist for the "Great Lakes Navy Bulletin". He then decided to move to New York to work as a freelance artist. He had much success furnishing cartoons, illustrations, and cover art for the the fledgling magazines "Life" and "The New Yorker". He also contributed to "Look", "Colliers", "Harper's Bazaar", "Saturday Evening Post", "Good Housekeeping", "Promenade", "Esquire", and others, but his most important work was with the "New Yorker", which put him under contract. He worked with "The New Yorker" for more than forty years giving them nearly 100 covers and several hundred cartoons. While living in New York he met Florence Semler. They were married in 1928 and continued to live in New York until they moved to Westport, Connecticut, where they spent the remainder of their days. When "Look" and "Colliers", two of Garrett's mainstays, shut down, Garrett began to submit more of his work to "Saturday Evening Post" and "Sports Illustrated". He also found time to illustrate several children's books and do a weekly cartoon for the Westport "Town Crier" called "Price Tags". Garrett spent the last few years of his life painting watercolors and relaxing in his Connecticut home. He died in 1979.
Scope and Content
The Garrett W. Price Papers contain mainly Price's artwork from 1918-1969, including cover illustrations for "The New Yorker" with drafts and sketches; cartoons; sketches and sketchbooks, including his works while in France and Mexico and a picture diary of those trips; advertisements; illustrations for books and book covers; and watercolors. The collection also contains diaries (1942-1973); correspondence with editors and his family (1909-1973); miscellaneous biographical information and photographs (1912-1976); and publications (1935-1968). The artwork gives a good representation of Garrett's professional work. From it one is able to discern the different periods of his professional life and artistic methods. Paricularly insightful are his personal notes attached to certain items that explain how he came up with an idea or what troubles he had getting it published. The correspondence, especially the notes and letters from magazine editors shows how much the artists had to do to get their work published.\\\
Access Restrictions
There are no access restrictions on the materials for research purposes, and the collection is open to the public.
Related Materials
There are no known other archival collections created by Garrett W. Price at the date of processing.
Acquisition Information
The Garrett W. Price papers were donated to the University of Wyoming in several accretions from 1970 to 1984 by Garrett W. Price and his wife, Florence.
Existence and Location of Copies
Digital reproductions of select material from this collection are available at https://digitalcollections.uwyo.edu/luna/servlet/uwydbuwy~167~167.
Access Terms
Cartoonists--United States.; Illustration of books--United States.; Magazine illustration--United States.; Mexico--History--1970-1988.; France--History--1945-; Diaries.; Cartoons (humorous images).; Illustrations.; Artists.; The New Yorker.
Arts, Humanities, and Social Sciences; Fine Arts; Literature; Publishers and Publishing
Container List
- Series I. Artwork
  - Sub-series 1. Cover Illustrations
    - "New Yorker" Covers, 1925-1964 (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
    - "New Yorker" Cover Drafts--Sports Themes, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - "New Yorker" Cover Drafts, undated (Box 1, Folder 4-11)
    - "New Yorker" Cover Drafts, undated (Box 2, Folder 1-4)
    - Miscellaneous Covers--"Life", "McCalls", and "Colliers", 1925-1955 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Subseries 2. Cartoons
    - Clippings from "Colliers", ca. 1945-1955 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Color Magazine Covers, ca. 1940s (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Editorial Cartoons--"Great Lakes Navy Bulletin", 1918-1919 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - "Life" Cartoons, 1929-1933 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Cartoons Clipped from Unlabeled Magazines, 1928-1955 (Box 2, Folder 10-12)
    - "New Yorker" Cartoons, 1928-1945 (Box 2, Folder 13-14)
    - "New Yorker" Cartoons, ca. 1945-1955 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Cartoon Drafts and Instructions for the "New Yorker", undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Office of War Information Cartoons, 1942-1944 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Original Pencil Cartoons, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Originals and Drafts, ca. 1940s-1950s (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - "Price Tags" Clippings, 1965-1968 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - "Price Tags" Drafts and Instructions, undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Proofs, 1932-1937 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Sketches and Roughs, undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Rough Drafts and Originals, 1924-1950s (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Rough Drafts, undated (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - "Saturday Evening Post" Clippings, ca. 1940s (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - "Tide" Magazine Clippings, 1931-1932 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Clippings from Various Magazines, undated (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Western Theme Cartoon Clippings, 1940-1968 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Western Theme Drafts and Originals, undated (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Western Theme Original Pencil Drawings, undated (Box 3, Folder 17-19)
  - Subseries 3. Sketches/Sketchbooks
    - Caricatures and Sketches of Acquaintances (Sketch by James Cagney removed to Safe), undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Pencil Drawings, 1922-1936 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Charcoal Drawings and Lithographs of Paris, 1925-1928 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Charcoal and Pencil Drawings, and Lithograph of Paris, Marseilles, Florence, and Venice, 1925-1928 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Sketchbook--Paris, 1928 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Sketchbooks--Paris and France, 1928 (Box 4, Folder 6-7)
    - Sketchbooks, 1932-1936 (Box 4, Folder 8-9)
    - Sketchbook--Mexico, 1936 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Sketchbooks, 1937-1938 (Box 4, Folder 11-12)
    - Sketchbooks, 1939-1952 (Box 5, Folder 1-4)
    - Sketchbook--Trip to the West, 1949 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Sketchbook, 1955-1962 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Sketchbook--Trip to the West, 1958 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Subseries 4. Advertisements
    - Assorted Advertisements, 1930-1954 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Bell Telephone Advertisements, 1940 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Advertisements--Esso Motor Oil, General Chemical, and Sal Hepatica, 1932-1939 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Advertisements--International Nickel Co., Ohrbach, Manning and Brown, 1938-1943 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Macy's Department Store Advertisements, 1938-1939 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Subseries 5. Illustrations
    - Book Cover Illustrations, undated (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Illustrations--"Chicago Tribune", and "Liberty", 1925-1931 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Magazine and Newspaper Illustrations, 1920s-1930s (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - "Life" and Men's Magazines Illustrations, 1930s-1940s (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Women's Magazines--"Ladies Home Journal", "McCalls", etc., 1930s-1940s (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Sending Photo by Wire, 1966 (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - McCutchen-Cornwell Memorial Dinner, 1969 (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - "That Dog, That Cat"--Booklet, undated (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - "We Keep Plugging"--Fish Story, undated (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - Wyoming Themes--Drafts and Originals, undated (Box 6, Folder 15)
- Series II. Diaries
  - Diaries, 1942-1944 (Box 7, Folder 1-4)
  - Diary--Wartime, 1944-1945 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Diaries, 1945-1955 (Box 7, Folder 6-11)
  - Diaries, 1955-1973 (Box 8, Folder 1-2)
- Series III. Publications
  - "Drawing Room Only"--Garrett W. Price, 1946 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - "The Honey Boat"--Illustrated by Garrett W. Price, 1968 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - "Meet the Artist", 1943 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - "The New Yorker Album, 1950-1955" (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - "Stage" Magazine, 1935 (Box 8, Folder 7)
- Series IV. Correspondence
  - General Correspondence, 1909-1973, undated (Box 9, Folder 1-2)
  - General Correspondence (Letters from Walter Winchell, Rube Goldberg and James Thurber removed to Safe), 1947-1973 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Critiques and Rejections--from "The New Yorker" and Other Magazines, 1933-1963 (Box 9, Folder 4-6)
    Restriction: Correspondence from The New Yorker may not be photocopied or reproduced.
- Series V. Biographical/Miscellaneous Material
  - Certificates and Awards, 1944-1971 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Geology Notebooks--from University of Wyoming Class, 1914 (Box 9, Folder 8-9)
  - News Clippings--Re: Garrett W. Price, 1912-1973 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - News Clippings--Miscellaneous, 1930s-1961 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Purvis, Clara--Miscellaneous Items (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Photographs, undated (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - Von Schmidt, Harold--Article and Sketch, 1970-1971 (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - Items Written by Garrett W. Price--Poetry and Remembrances, undated (Box 9, Folder 15)
- Series I. Artwork
  - Sub-series 2. Cartoons
    - Cartoons--Originals and Drafts, ca. 1940s (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Cartoons/Illustrations--Drafts and Originals for "The New Yorker", undated (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Cover Illustrations--Originals and Covers--Paintings, Drawings and Pastels, 1925-1949 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Cover Illustrations--Originals and Covers--Paintings, Drawings, and Crayon, 1950-1963 (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Cover Illustrations--Originals and Drafts--Paintings, Drawings, and Crayon, undated (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - Cover Illustrations--Paintings, undated (Box 10, Folder 6)
- Series I. Artwork
  - Sub-series 3. Sketches/Sketchbooks
    - Sketches and Lithographs of Paris, 1925 (Box 10, Folder 7)
- Series I. Artwork
  - Sub-series 5. Illustrations
    - Illustrations, ca. 1920s-1950s (Box 10, Folder 8)
- Series V. Miscellaneous Material
  - Newspapers, 1912-1971 (Box 11, Folder 1)
- Series I. Artwork
  - Sub-series 6. Watercolor Paintings
    - Watercolors--Mexico and Martha's Vineyard, ca.1936 (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - Watercolors and Paintings, undated (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - Watercolor Painting of Mexican Landscape, 1936 (Oversize Folder 1)